The following content is provided under a Creative
Commons license.
Your support will help MIT OpenCourseWare continue to
offer high quality educational resources for free.
To make a donation or view additional materials from
hundreds of MIT courses, visit MIT OpenCourseWare at
ocw.mit.edu.
So today I want to talk with you about how it is that we can
do research of a scientific kind for something as complex as
human behavior, as opposed to things that you measure out
in space or test tubes or under microscopes.
People are complex organisms, right?
And to do research on them, to understand human nature, how
the mind works, how the brain supports it, is a
challenging story.
So the usual thing is an experiment.
You have a group of participants who will talk
about that.
But in the reading for today, and I know for the first time
we've done this, so you may not have read it, but if you
have, that'd be great, is another thread of the kind of
way that people are studied, which is dramatic
individual stories, case studies, single stories that
are illustrative of something that we think are
broader principles.
And a lot of our biggest discoveries, and we'll come
to that later in the course, have been made on very
unusual single individuals who turn out to have a lesson
that's pretty broad, for example, for the
organization, the human brain.
So in the Oliver Sacks book, there's a story about Donald.
And what did Donald do that got him in big trouble?
He murdered his girlfriend while he was on PCP.
He's in a psychiatric hospital.
They try hypnosis to help him remember it.
He says he doesn't remember it.
Many of you may know that an astounding number of
criminals under interrogation tell you they don't
remember anything about the episode involved.
So people are suspicious at first, for many reasons,
because the easiest thing to say is I don't remember what
happened, and then you can't catch yourself in a lie or
any complexity, because you don't remember what happened.
And sometimes you don't remember, and sometimes you do.
But in this case, they try hypnosis.
That doesn't help.
He's in there for four years.
And then he knows conceptually that he murdered his
girlfriend, and he says, I'm not fit for society.
He knows it's a terrible thing he did.
But it's kind of like an intellectual knowledge, right?
It's not a feeling.
It's not a memory.
And then he goes biking and something happens.
Which is, he gets hit by a car.
And so there's what appears to be a drug-induced amnesia of
the original murderous episode.
He gets hit by a car.
He has a severe head injury.
He's in a coma for two weeks.
He has left-sided weakness as he comes out of it, which
means the biggest injury was in the right side of his brain.
Weakness and numbness.
And he has frontal lobe contusions.
He has injury and bleeding around the frontal lobes,
the cortex that sits in the front of the brain.
But now a remarkable thing happens.
It's as if two insults, two wrongs made a right.
The first wrong being the PCP, the second wrong being the
accident, and now what happens?
He remembers in vivid and florid detail the horror that he
actually committed this murder.
It's as if two insults to the brain, one drug-induced, one
a focal injury, repressed the memory, and
then unrepressed the memory.
And one of the first things I have to do is discover whether
he really has his memory or he just thinks he has his
memory.
And how do they figure out to their satisfaction whether it's
a really recovered memory or a fabrication of his mind?
Right, that's really important.
He remembers details of the murder that are not publicly
available, that were not in the information that was given
to him.
That's a really huge issue in these kinds of memories.
So there's a really recovered memory, not an
inadvertently fabricated memory.
And they discover he has deep seizure activity in his limb
structures, the parts of his brain that are involved in
emotion are having seizures.
In epilepsy, neurons are firing for no good reason, and
that's part of his disorder.
They give him medications to help with that.
But here's the question for you for a moment to think about.
And it's now such a common question because our society
is moving that way, that it's on many TV shows.
I see it every couple of weeks.
There's a Law and Order episode that has something like
this, which is the more you know about the biology that
underlies really criminal, terrible behavior.
Should that be a cause for understanding it, or not?
So in this case, he took the drugs, he killed the person,
you think he's pretty responsible.
But how about somebody who kills somebody, and it turns
out, in such a case, a man with no history, a grown man
with no history of criminal activity of any kind, shoved
his wife out of a high window to her death in the course of
a standard argument.
Then they discovered that he has a big tumor growing in the
basal part of his frontal cortex.
Now, is the man responsible for what he did?
It's a really interesting question, right?
And the more we understand about the neuroscience of our
brains, what makes us do things which lets us control
impulses, what makes us murderous, there's a guy, Kent
Keele, University of Mexico, who's driving around in a big
van with an MRI scanner, and he goes from penitentiary to
penitentiary, and he images the brains of serial
murderers, of psychopathic murderers.
And he's getting things that are pretty systematically
different about their brains.
And the question is, what does that mean?
Does that mean those people were prone to do it for
reasons of their early environment, or genes, or
some incident that happened?
If that's the case, do you forgive them differently?
Should we have a different moral code, or legal code as we
discovered the brain basis for some of these things?
Or is that irrelevant, what counts as the action?
So this is the kind of thing you could think about, maybe
discuss in your section some.
The more we understand about the human brain, the more we'll
understand about behaviors that we find terrible.
And what does that mean about legal and moral decisions about
how to punish those, or think about those?
So that's coming in your lifetime, because there's
steady progress on this, and how to think about that is a
really big question.
So I'm going to talk with you today about research and
psychology.
And a funny thing about psychology, and I'll come
back to this, is everybody is an amateur psychologist.
They have to be.
If you deal with people, you're an amateur psychologist.
Moreover, we live in a world with Oprah Winfrey and Dr.
Phil, right?
So in case you're only an amateur one, you hear all
kinds of stuff, newspaper, internet, magazines,
everywhere you go, friends will tell you stuff about
psychologists have found this, or
psychologists have found that.
So you have your own intuitions to deal with people in
everyday life.
And here's a kind of a sentence from Time Magazine that
drives psychologists crazy if you take it seriously.
So here's this literal sentence.
Almost half of children of divorces enter adulthood as
worried, underachieving, self-deprecating, and
sometimes angry young men and women.
OK.
So that sounds kind of like a psychological study of
some kind, kind of, right?
Somebody who wants to argue about the importance of
divorce and breakdown of the family.
So let's think about this for a moment.
Almost half of children of divorce enter adulthood as
worried.
Are you guys worried about global warming?
A little.
Are you worried about peace in the Middle East and how that
influences the Middle East and the US?
A little.
Are you worried about an economy that may not have
jobs waiting for you?
A little.
OK.
Who's not worried?
A little.
A little bit of the time.
So it doesn't even tell you that half of children in the
world, for example, are who come from families.
Without divorce, right?
Because that's the only relevant question.
It's not are people worried about stuff.
Underachieving, compared to what?
How would you prove somebody's underachieving?
Scientifically.
I mean, most of you probably have had days where you've
underachieved and days where you've achieved pretty well.
But how would you measure and prove that?
Self-deprecating.
Well, sometimes we think it's actually kind of nice if a
person's modest.
What's the difference between modest and self-deprecation?
And I like this one.
Sometimes angry young men and women, right?
I mean, are you sometimes angry about something or another?
And if you are, does that tell us that society is breaking
down and your parents did something bad that you're
sometimes?
I mean, who as a human being is not sometimes angry?
So here's a kind of psychology-sounding sentence on a
serious topic, which is what is consequences of
divorces in families?
Should we be thinking about things that encourage
marriages to stay stable and things like that?
But there's really no information at all.
So from a researcher science perspective, so I'm going to
talk about a little bit, just reminding you what science is.
We're at a university, obviously, that thinks about
science and does science all the time.
Remind you of what an experiment is, a very brief
history of psychology experimentation, and then walk
you through a few experiments that I find kind of
interesting, and then some topics related to psychology.
So let me start with this.
How do you know what is true?
That you take to be true?
What is the answer?
Everyone's looking all like, how do I know?
Please tell me.
OK.
Well, when people try to analyze this, and you can think
about it for your own self, one of them is authority.
Parents, teachers, textbooks, scientists, professors, and
courses, we tell you this is the truth.
And if you remember the truth correctly, you get an A.
So authority is a huge source.
It would be costly to go around and kind of have your own
idea about everything.
12 inches in a foot, I'm not taking that piece of
information without skepticism.
You couldn't lead your life without kind of believing a
lot of stuff, but you know you don't want to believe
everything, just because you hear it.
Repetition or tenacity, you hear something often enough,
and people tend to believe stuff.
A priori, what's reasonable?
You think things through just by thought.
What's possible, rational, and so on?
And then maybe a fourth brand of knowledge to something
scientific analysis, where we have hypotheses and we test
them in some version of experiments, or at least
correlations among data.
Now there's another view, which is kind of that whatever we
think makes something science is what the scientific
community decides as a community is true.
Roughly speaking, that is the mainstay of faculty at
places like MIT and Stanford and Harvard and so on, and
around the world at universities tell you this is
how science works, you go, OK, that's how
science works.
And I remember some years ago, there was a lot of excitement
about a satirical article written by a scientist,
where he said, oh, this is all just societal authority.
The scientists tell you what's true, just because they
believe in it, just like a sports writer says the
Celtics are the best.
You don't really think that the sports writer knows
scientifically the Celtics are the best, right?
OK.
So he wrote a paper saying that gravity is simply a
consensus among scientists, and a particular view they're
foisting on society.
But none of us would want to really go up there and jump
out the window going, well, gravity is one person's
opinion, and here's my opinion, right?
But it's kind of interesting, because for those of you who
go to medical school, for example, you'll learn lots of
procedures and so on that the medical community believes
is true, where there's not much scientific evidence behind
it, but they have to use it every day.
So you're used to hearing about the scientific method.
It applies to psychology in many ways, just like it applies
to chemistry, physics, or biology.
We have to test things that are falsifiable.
We have to deal in probabilities of outcomes in terms of
statistics in some sense.
The kinds of data we can have are descriptive, or
correlative, or experimental.
I'll talk about those in a moment.
We are always trying to disprove the null hypothesis
statistically, as you know.
We can't prove that something is true, but we can prove
that it's not true.
And then finally, like all fields of science, today's
most exciting breakthroughs are tomorrow's things that have
to be apologized for and rediscovered, right?
I mean, what makes something breaking science is not that
it's known with certainty.
What's known with certainty is what's in your textbook,
kind of.
What makes something breaking science is it moves the
field forward, so what's the difference between the cutting
edge and the bleeding edge is a very close call.
So here's a cartoon that says he's constantly proving his
experiments wrong, and the guy's kind of glum looking over.
He's proving the null hypothesis to be correct.
Now, that's sort of funny for scientists.
But it's sort of funny in the sense that, no, we don't
really go around going, I hope, you know, with all my
heart for this research project I've worked on for the last
five years that it will prove the null hypothesis.
There's no difference between things I'm studying.
In fact, scientists like all humans have agendas and hopes,
and like everybody else.
So they observe hypothesized experiment, assess data, and
it doesn't always go perfectly, right?
And the last thing I want to say is I'm going to emphasize
today a scientific approach to the human mind and behavior.
But of course, there's many other paths of knowledge for
important things in our life, religion, philosophy,
arts, and so on.
There's many things that science cannot address, and I
don't want to pretend that it does.
That's not a problem too much when you think about chemistry.
It's kind of an interesting problem when you think about
psychology, because when we think about happiness or values
or things like that, those topics cut across psychology and
things like religion, philosophy, and topics like that.
So what makes something an experiment is you have to have
sort of two things, conceptually, especially.
The dependent variable, what you measure, the outcome, and
the independent variable, what you vary.
Once you have those things in an experiment, you're kind of
an experiment in a broad sense.
So in psychology, it took a long time.
It wasn't until the 1800s that people had kind of an
approach to doing experiments in psychology.
And figuring out, for example, how to use the simple
measurement of time to measure how long a mental
operation lasts in your mind.
So that's pretty cool.
If you were to come to a fifth grader and say, how would you
measure not a brick or a stone, but how long a thought takes?
You would say, well, that would be pretty hard.
But it turns out it's not as hard in a simple way.
So Wilhelm Wundt, who, big figure in psychology, first
textbook in psychology, first laboratory in psychology, did
the following test of mental chronometry, simply measuring
how long it takes you to do things.
So he would show you a light, and he'd simply press the
button, and that would take about a fifth of a second.
And then he would say, instead, let's you do this.
If the light turns on and it's red, you push one button, and
if it's green, you push another.
So his idea was, the motor system to push the button is
about the same.
The time to observe the light is about the same.
But the difference between these two is how long it takes
to make a choice.
How long it takes to make a choice.
And that difference, when he subtracts them, took about a
tenth of a second by that measurement.
So all of a sudden, you could start to measure, in an
objective sense, how long a mental operation
takes in your mind.
Then psychology went a lot of different directions.
A famous one from Tichner, who worked with Wundt, developed
the psychology department at Cornell, was introspection.
Look inside yourself and think very carefully when you think
about a topic.
How do I think about it?
That lost its way as a scientific method.
Trouble is, one person thinks one way, and one person
thinks another way, and you can't really settle it, right?
So introspection about your thoughts is a private process.
It's not a public measure that you can exchange among
scientists, like time or measurements.
But we still introspect a lot when we think about psychology,
whether it feels right to us, whether the questions
to ask are still just being human.
You can't help but introspect about psychology topics.
In the US, there was a huge response to introspection as
being too loosey-goosey.
One famous name, and this is John Watson, he said, the mind
is unobservable.
So we can only study behavior, things that people do.
Actions they take.
Their mouth moves, their hand buttons, presses.
And then we identify what in the environment influences
those behaviors.
The principles of the mind should be similar between
animals and humans, and the only thing a responsible
experimental scientist can do is relate environmental
factors to actions.
And so there's a stimulus, and you can control the
stimulus as a scientist.
There's a response, you measure the response.
And that's your psychology experiment.
And then the 1980s became the cognitive revolution.
Partly, this path led, after a while, to not very
interesting science.
That was the biggest problem.
And people said, no, we can make inferences about the mind
as it translates what it hears or sees
into what a person does.
So ideas of representations or knowledge in the mind, or in
the brain later on, and how that translates what's out
there, and how you act upon it.
So I'll remind you a couple more things
then we'll get to specifics.
So correlations are, you can only get in an experiment,
where you have an independent variable.
Sorry, correlations you can look at all the time.
Experiments only, experiments allows
us to infer causation.
So let's pick an example that, when I read, struck me as
slightly relevant.
So age of parent and risk for disease in a child.
So most of you are young enough that you're not too
worried about this yet, and you have no reason to be.
But for those of us who are in my generation and some
generations back, many people are postponing childbirth, as
they do their careers in complete different tasks.
And parents are getting older and older.
They're only seem old, they are old.
So it's the case statistically that the older the mother is
that higher the risk of Down syndrome.
So the statistics are, if a mother is age 20 to 24, it's
very rare to have Down syndrome, and the number goes up
dramatically if the mother is over age 42.
So this is simple observation and measurement, but it's
something a lot of women giving birth in their 30s and 40s
are thinking about and worrying about, and it's a
thing on their mind.
Up until relatively recently, men said, oh, it's too bad for
those women, but no problem for us.
So you have the movie star, who's 90 years old and
marries a 20-year-old actress.
That kind of model that you see all the time in the news.
Because it doesn't matter how old the guy is.
Well, it turns out it does matter.
And here's some data for that.
So here's the probability of developing schizophrenia, a
disease that's typically diagnosed in a person's late
adolescence or 20s, depending on the age of the father.
And you can see the father is less than 25.
It's 1 out of 141.
If the father is in his 50s, it becomes 1 out of 50, a
dramatic growth in the likelihood of an offspring
child having schizophrenia, depending on the age of the
father.
So now, there's a correlation between age and whether a
child expresses schizophrenia.
So let's guess about the possible causes of that.
I can tell you it's unknown.
But let's even begin to guess about it.
Let me ask you to guess about it.
Yeah?
Maybe the damage by age and under the lack of
augmentation.
Yeah, bad sperm.
OK, for some reason in some way.
And sperm that leads more likely to be risk for
schizophrenia.
So that's your first intuition.
And that may turn out to be right, problematic.
Something problematic about the sperm from the male.
Here's another one, though.
And this shows you the challenges with
correlational research on something even so important
as this, which is, how about a long-term
alternative, which is, who marries later in life?
OK?
Maybe the desirable moment are plucked off the market on
average in large statistics by age 30 or something.
And a bunch of us, and I'm a late marrier, limp to find
some woman around the world who will accept us.
And finally, out of pity, some woman says, OK, you drag
yourself into your 50s, and I'll take you.
So right, because it's not random, probably.
We're averaging over many people, but it's not random
probably, who marries at 25 in a given society, and who
marries at 50?
It's not random.
It could be big differences among, OK?
And how could we tell that difference?
Maybe it's nothing to do with the sperm.
Maybe it's something to do with the, something about the
genes and environment that goes with marrying, being a
parent in your 50s versus being a parent in your 20s.
Completely different explanations.
Someday maybe we'll know, but we don't know now.
So this is the limits of correlations.
And it could be both could be true.
Neither could be a third story altogether.
So that was about me, my becoming a parent late in
life, and marrying late in life.
Let's talk about you, all right?
So let's talk about the level of stress you have, and how
empathetic you are, on average, your college generation
relative to one's five or 10 or 20 years ago.
So let's ask that question.
Why would people want to know such a thing?
Well, you might want to understand, what pressures
are we putting young people under as they go through
grade school and high school and college?
What's the world like?
Is it pretty much the same?
Is it pretty much changing?
Now, how would we figure that out?
How would we begin to measure that?
It's a very simple question.
Are you more stressed than people 10 years ago at MIT?
On average, across the country?
And are you more or less empathetic towards other
people?
How might one answer that kind of a question?
Yeah?
For the stress part, we know a little bit about
the form of the city extent that we can then
involve one another for any stress.
That would be a very interesting path.
It's a tough research path, but you're right.
If we had some biological signature of stress, that
would be a good one.
But let's ask this question.
Let's say I measured everybody in here and got your
average stress hormone or something like that.
Now, what's my answer about whether 10 years ago, people
were more or less stressed?
Yeah?
Look at suicide rates.
That would be an outcome of a kind.
But there's a lot of things that go in.
We have to worry about two things.
One thing we know is, let me ask you another one, you
could compare your level of stress to people who are
10 years older than you or 20 years older than you.
What do you think about that?
No?
Yeah?
It would actually be more accurate if you
measured who you want to know for a college student
specifically.
You'd have to get a baseline of yourself from somewhere
like before.
Yeah, because maybe people who are 30 or 40
are more stressed for other reasons, because they have
more bills and mortgages to pay or less stress for other
reasons or whatever.
Maybe that's not about the generation you're in.
Maybe it's about being a person with more responsibilities
at 40.
So for some things, you get some luck.
And you have it in your hand.
So here's an emotional health questionnaire
where students across the country for the last 25 years
have been given the identical questionnaire.
It's a questionnaire, it's not a biology measure,
about their self-reported measure of stress.
And this was in the New York Times just a few weeks ago.
It's you guys on average across the country, US college
students, are at an all-time, high level of self-reported
stress.
Sorry about that.
So now it's not the perfect measurement in every way,
but it's the same questionnaire to college students year
and year out.
By self-report, people say, I feel more stressed.
You can also see that there's a difference between men
and women.
Women on average report feeling more stressed.
And it may be relevant, and on average, for example,
there's a higher rate of depression among women than men.
There's a much higher rate of autism among men than women.
So it's not a being one sex or the other is not
a gift certificate of avoiding mental health challenges.
But so you're more stressed than ever, OK?
Good luck.
We'll try to do the best we can in this course,
not we'll make that way worse.
But that's something to think about.
I got a call the other day from somebody
who said there's a lot of curiosity
about whether the shift from book learning and book
reading to internet worlds and Twitter and Facebook worlds
are fundamentally changing how people think.
And that sounds kind of possible.
And there are people who give amazingly entertaining
lectures about these things.
Scientifically, it's unbelievably hard
to imagine how we would ever answer that.
So when I get a casual phone call,
like, what do neuroscientists know about that?
What could they know about it?
Is that even an answerable question?
If I take you now and say, well, you've probably
done more Facebook than a 50-year-old,
and compare you to a 50-year-old on some other thing,
is that going to answer the question of how you think
about ideas given the world you live in versus the world
a 50-year-old lived in?
No.
So there's just a lot of huge, deep things
about changes in the world that we can't even
begin to get at.
Sometimes we get lucky if people have been giving
some particular measure for some time.
Empathy by self-reports.
And now you, if this, I wouldn't fill it out now,
but you can take a look just to get a feeling
of your leisure.
This is a questionnaire they used for self-reported empathy.
It's self-report 40% lower today than 20 years ago.
So on average, you guys, literally
on average by these measures, are
more stressed and less empathetic towards others.
Sorry.
And those things, this is not an individual.
This is an average.
So at the level that society operates,
things are going on and moving for some reason.
By the way, I can tell you that when I'm stressed,
I have less room to be empathetic.
So maybe these things are related.
If you're feeling stressed, your first thought
is not how can I help others, but how can I just
get through the day?
So these things might be related.
So let's turn a little bit to experimentation.
And some of the challenges of relating psychology
to real world policies that are meant
to make the world better or safer in some way.
So there's a famous broken window theory
from the political scientist James Wilson, the criminologist
George Kelling.
And their idea was this, that especially in neighborhoods
that are not immaculately kept, or to say it the other way,
where there's a lot of damage around you,
things like broken windows is the phrase they used,
that this promotes in people who live in that community
or work around that community a sense that the rules don't
count, anybody can do anything.
And then it fosters the growth of petty crimes.
And once you do a petty crime, you're more vulnerable
or willing to do a major crime, a slippery slope.
And in fact, Rudy Giuliani and Commissioner Bill Bretton
employ this.
They ask the police to write lots of tickets
and make lots of minor arrests for things
where people weren't upkeeping the environment
or they were littering or things like that.
And this is a huge debate, because in a police department,
you can only do so much.
So if they have a person working on jaywalking and littering,
that's a person not working on major crime rings, OK?
So to try to make a choice where they think
they can make communities safer in the most effective way.
And the crimes went way down in New York.
In most cities now, you don't hear crime discussed
as a big topic nationally in some local areas,
like in Boston, in some specific areas you do.
I don't really think in the state of the Union
there was a word about crime that I can remember a week ago.
It's not a big national topic.
In some local places, it is a big topic, but not nationally.
So you don't know some years ago when people said New York
City was a horrible place to go because there was so much
crime that you'd walk out from your airplane
and get mugged before you made it to your taxi.
No, it was like the whole country was saying
big cities were just crime-ridden and dangerous.
They do this policy, things get better, right?
So we said, hm, that sounds pretty good.
But of course, it's not an experiment.
It's a real-life policy.
And then people had these incredibly clever reinterpretations
of why crime went down.
So the wildest one was in Freakonomics,
was discussed in that, which said, well, abortion
was legalized in 1973.
That gave women who didn't have access
to legal abortions the ability to have them,
that children on average in these communities
had at least access to safe and legal abortions
would be poor and stable addiction-ridden communities
statistically.
And that's so that if you imagine the reduced abortion
rate in poor areas could, when you count out
the number of possible criminals in those areas,
account for the reduction in crime all by itself.
A completely different interpretation
that has nothing to do with the policy.
It just said, we're going to have a demographic shift, which
will have a weird, unexpected consequence of lowering
the crime rate, because it's the finding
that young men in particular are most likely to engage
in violent criminal activities.
Not a rule, but a statistical average.
Or there was a big crack academic that reduced,
or lots of states put in laws that put people into jail
for much higher, longer periods, much more
severe penalties with new drug laws.
So it's very hard to know if the policy that was initiated
really worked, or whether completely other things were
happening that move the crime rates.
And here's some very perverse or other explanations.
So that left the question is, is broken windows
even a good idea?
Just because a Harvard, and we know Harvard is always right,
but just because a Harvard psychologist says,
pretty interestingly, that sounds right to me,
is that even a right idea?
So let's take a step back.
Can we test that experimentally?
So here's the experiment.
And the idea is, again, that when people observe that others
violate a social norm or legitimate rule,
are they more likely to violate?
If you see people around you breaking rules,
are you more likely to do it?
And you could say, it seems like it is, but let's do the science.
So here's an independent measure.
I'll show you the environment.
The dependent measure is in the number
of people who perform a violation.
Now, you can't go getting people murdering each other
and stuff for an experiment, but you can do this.
You can have two conditions.
On the top condition, do you ever go back to your car or bike?
Usually cars, I think.
And they put leaflets in your car,
and now what are you going to do?
You're running away with a leaflet on your windshield wiper.
So they put it out, and they either
had a wall like this, which was clean.
There's a sign that says no graffiti.
And they put on those white pieces of paper onto the bikes,
or they put a lot of graffiti on the wall.
People came out from their classes.
They went in the glasses.
They parked their bike.
They ran into class.
They came out, and they got all these white leaflets.
And what they did is watched, and they
said how many people put the leaflet away,
and how many people crumpled it up and threw it right on the ground.
So we don't know what they're going to do with the leaflet
that they put it away, but we could hope
they're going to throw it out.
One thing we know for sure, if you crumpled up and throw it
on the ground, it's littering and not a good social norm.
And sure enough, a third of the people
littered if the wall had no graffiti,
but it more than doubled if the wall had graffiti.
So that's a small thing.
That's not a broken down, complicated neighborhood.
But just at that moment, as you roar out of class,
you get that piece of paper on your bike,
and you see like, wow, this is a pretty crummy place.
People are breaking the rules all the time.
Twice as likely to throw a piece of paper on the ground.
So that shows that people very easily
are influenced by very mild perceptions of whether people
are following the rules or not.
And will be their better selves or their worse selves,
depending on that sense of, are all rules on or are all rules off.
And there's a pretty good bet they're not thinking about it,
right?
They're not thinking they're saying they're, okay,
here's a, you know, here's littering, you know,
not as bad as killing somebody, or here's the wall,
well, there's 30% graffiti.
I mean, nobody does that.
They have an emotion, quick response,
but the environment makes a difference in that regard.
So an important thing about studies like this,
so let me tell you about this one.
Here's a study to look at a drug that was supposed
to lower mortality from coronary artery disease.
Those who took the drug, 80% or more,
because people follow whether you take the drug.
If you don't take the drug, of course, the drug won't work.
I had a 15% mortality rate within five years.
Those who took the drug, less than 80%
had a 25% mortality.
So you'd say, well, 10% better chance of living
for five years, that's worth it, right?
The nice thing is they had a placebo
and there was no difference whatsoever
between those who took the active drug
and those who took the placebo.
The differences between, was those who followed
the instructions to take the pill.
And those who didn't.
So what does that mean?
How do you interpret that?
It's not the drug.
Yeah?
It could be the stress of not following the drug,
it's not working for the drug.
It could be that.
It could be the stress, it could be that.
Let me make a guess.
There's no scientific answer to this.
People who tend not to follow instructions,
are they mostly stressed by not following instructions?
No, mostly the intuition is they're blowing it off.
They're like, yeah, that's the instructions,
but I got things to do in places to go.
But you could be right.
So anyway, the idea is, what you pick up is,
are people who try to take care of themselves.
They have a health condition,
and the people who are following the pill instruction
are probably also doing the best they can
in terms of exercise, diet, all the things they could do
to maximize their health, right?
And they're taking their placebo
or they're taking the drug, they don't know.
But they're doing everything they can.
And the people who are blowing off stuff,
they're the ones who are doing all the things
that aren't healthy, including not even taking your pills.
I mean, if you don't even take your pills, right?
Exercise is work, diet is work,
popping a pill that's been handed to you
that you're told might help you,
is probably not that much work.
So it's what's called self-selection bias,
that you stand out if you tend to take care
of yourself or not.
Okay, so when we run experiments
at universities that involve people,
a huge issue for us is the idea is this,
that we randomly recruit people,
and we'll come back to this in a moment,
then we randomly assign them to one condition or another,
for example, the placebo condition or the drug condition,
or we randomly assign them to the messy wall
or the clean wall.
We discover something and then we try to generalize it
as far as we can to people as a whole.
We've discovered something fundamental
about how humans work,
generalizable principles of human mind and behavior.
So what really happens in the world?
And it's always, you're in between
sort of the best possible world
in the world we actually live in.
So is it really, is it really random
who participates in research studies
in psychology departments where a lot of the research
gets done?
Is it really random?
No, okay.
So who volunteers?
Have any of you volunteered to be a subject
in an experiment anywhere?
Yeah.
Okay, so it's not random, you know,
it's that some people, they either need to make a few bucks
or they're very curious about psychology
or they have a friend who's in psychology
or, you know, it's not random.
And in fact, population-wide,
people have said that psychology can be described
as weird research for the following reason.
That the vast majority of the findings
you'll read about everywhere,
including in your textbook,
but everywhere are from nations that are westernized,
educated, industrialized and relatively rich democracies.
Okay?
The vast majority are between 17 and 25.
They're undergraduates or graduate students
who participate in research.
It's been estimated if you're a U.S. college student,
you're 4,000 times more likely to show up
in a scientifically reported experiment
than if you're a person anywhere else on the planet.
Okay?
4,000 times.
Because why?
Because it's changing a little bit,
but for many, many years, you know,
the huge amount of research happened in the U.S.
at universities, pretty much at better universities,
pretty much at highly selected students.
All right?
So that's, and then we never publish that.
We never say MIT students did the following things.
People just go, yeah, MIT students, you know,
because then we have a different report from Stanford
or from UMass or from Michigan or Texas.
We say, no, humans did an experiment
and humans are like this, okay?
So, and that could make us, you know,
it's just something to think about as you see studies
and stuff like that.
And people are more and more sensitized to that.
As the more and more of the world gets somewhat industrializes,
there's more and more research around the world,
but still the vast majority of findings are you guys, okay?
Now, that's just to start with who's in the subject pool
or the participant pool.
How normal are you when you do an experiment?
Are you like yourself or are you doing weird stuff?
And people use this idea that you're really weird
when you do an experiment in another sense,
because you're like, you don't know what's going on,
you're following instructions, you know?
So they do experiments to show how ridiculously
people behave when they're doing an experiment
like they would never do it.
So they ask them to come in and they say,
would you fill out 200 sheets of paper
filled with random digits, add them pairwise,
and just I'll come back in a few hours.
Now, if a friend asks you to do that,
add random digits for a couple hours,
you would be like, no, thank you.
I've got about 8 million better things to do than that, right?
I could multiply random digits to start with her.
So, but people will do it for hours
because they're in this weird like,
I mean, that's the instruction
and that's what my mission is.
Or even more ridiculous, they pick up a card
after each page, they've added all these numbers,
for no good reason, and the instruction tells them
when you've done the page,
tear the page up into 32 pieces.
And here's the next page, okay?
In the next page, it's obviously fruitless
and pointless, ridiculously so,
but because you're in an experiment
and somebody told you to do that, right?
You just keep barreling forward.
So, you know, how much are we or who we are
when we do experiments versus people
following weird instructions?
And we'll come back to that in some serious context.
That's the subject, how about experimenters?
Experimenters are never objective.
We try to be as scientist as objective as we can.
We're never, you know, we believe certain hypotheses,
we have certain goals, we recognize results
that would be super exciting,
we recognize results that would be boring.
Okay, we're humans too.
We wanna do stuff that matters,
we wanna do stuff that people reward us for.
I mean, it's just human.
So, here's a lowest case example
of how once you're an experimenter,
you produce your own results.
And believe me, it's much more when your result matters
for things like your career advancement
or your status in the field.
So, students were told that rats were either
maize bright or maize dull.
They were told that these rats were bred
to be smart learners or not so smart.
The rats were all just random rats, okay?
It's a fake story to undergraduates.
Then they had them test on a maize
and they said, for your laboratory exercise,
write down how quickly the rat runs the maize, okay?
And amazingly, the smart rats did way better
than the dull rats, okay?
Now, these are not students trying to become famous
or have a career, they're handing in an assignment, okay?
And how did that happen?
Well, they went back and it wasn't
that anybody faked data or anything like that,
but when they looked at films or discussed stuff
with kids, students in the course,
every little thing that the students did
that moved the data in tiny, tiny ways,
always favored finding the maize bright rats
and being brilliant maize runners.
So, for example, you know, they would put the rat,
if you've ever run a rat in a maize,
does anybody run a rat in a maize?
Is it easy?
If you pick them up and put them in the maize,
that's when they're more automated now.
Is it physically easy?
Are rats like, please, show me the starting line?
I'm ready to go?
No, what are they like?
Help me out here for you guys who've done this.
Are they kind of, are they kind of really at?
And they don't like to be handled that much, really, no.
Even ones in the other, they're just fighting.
And these are undergraduates who've hardly ever touched a rat.
Okay, they're like, please, don't attack me or something.
So they're holding up the guy and the rat's fighting back.
And because it's really uncomfortable,
that's really unhappy and the student's like, really,
so what happens is, and then they clunk the rat down
and they go, oh my gosh, it's facing the wrong direction
and it's a smart one.
Wait, let's start, stop the clock, let's get him,
but if it's a dull one facing the wrong direction,
it's okay, it's a dull one, let the maize,
so lots of little things.
Are you sure you wrote this down?
Was it 12 seconds or 11?
I guess it was 11, oh, because it's a smart one, okay?
So completely innocently, completely innocently,
as far as we understand, they made the result
to match up with what the expectation was.
And it's not just that, and if you know this example,
cognitive psychology has studied a phenomenon like this,
so try this at your desk.
Each card is a letter on one side
and a number on the other side.
Your job is to figure out what's the smallest number
of cards you have to pick up
to discover if this rule is right.
If a card has a vowel on one side,
then it has an even number on the other side.
So think about this for a moment.
If a card has a vowel on one side,
then it has to have an even number on the other side.
What's the smallest number of cards you can pick up
to test that hypothesis?
So here's what people have found.
The correct answer is E and seven,
and about 10% of people on average come up with that.
Many, many more people pick E alone or E and six.
Why?
Well, everybody gets that you have to look at E
because it's an even number, right?
So you flip E over, and if that one turns out to have,
it's a vowel, if it has an odd number,
that hypothesis is wrong, right?
That's, everybody gets it, you should check E.
Pretty much everybody gets that J is irrelevant
because it's a consonant, okay?
Now comes the interesting six and seven.
Because the sentence is talking about a vowel
and an even number, sometimes people feel like,
gotta check the even number, right?
But it doesn't say anything about even numbers
and couldn't go with consonants.
It doesn't even, it doesn't tell you anything.
That's not part of the hypothesis.
So you don't, but if you flipped over number seven
and you discovered a vowel, you'd violate the rule.
So what happens is they're tempted to go for things
that feel like they confirm the question.
And it feels like E confirms it
and it feels like six confirms it, right?
And it's what's called confirmatory bias.
That when you look at stuff,
if you see what you think confirms it,
then you tend to go for that
even when there's evidence in front of you
that could contradict your expectation.
Okay, so now I'm gonna give you a practical suggestion
for how to win somebody over
if you have a brewing romantic interest in that person,
all right?
All right, so finally we get practical, right?
Everything was like, I'm not running rats, you know?
I'm taking, all right, all right.
And I think it's really interesting
because I think, when we think about how people
make decisions in their lives,
we tend to think intuitively about big decisions.
You know, like, what's my career gonna be?
Where do I go to college?
We think those are the big decisions,
but a huge amount of life is little decisions.
Moment to moment, if somebody asks you for something,
do you say yes or no?
Somebody walks up to you at a party.
They want to talk with you.
Do you feel like talking or not feel like talking?
You know, maybe you talk with them
as a lifetime friend or a romantic partner or whatever.
So I think we make constantly little decisions
that turn out to big effects in our lives.
So here's some evidence about things like that
that influence that.
And this is, worked in at Yale.
So we describe people as warm,
or we can define them as cold or aloof, right?
And we could think those words are kind of arbitrary.
And most of us, if you met somebody at a party,
would you rather hang out with somebody
who's warm or cold?
Warm, okay.
All right, just checking that we're, okay.
Now, sometimes there's an idea of embodied cognition
and here's what it is.
We can't really know how warm or cold that person is,
or even that's even an abstract idea,
but we know we're comfortable when we're kind of warm
and we know we're not comfortable physically inside us
when we're kind of cold.
So there's an idea that when we think about
other people's feelings, other people's thoughts,
or abstract things in the world,
we base them on physical experiences that we have inside,
okay, that there's a more direct link
between what we know inside us
and we use that to interpret the world out there.
And embodied cognition, your body is the vehicle
for understanding things out there.
So here's the experiment, it's really clever.
There's two temperature conditions.
So what happens is you go into a building
and the examiner, an undergraduate,
usually a graduate student, meets a subject in the lobby
and he's carrying a cup of coffee.
Sometimes it's hot coffee, sometimes it's cold coffee.
A clipboard, two textbooks, okay?
So you can imagine, it's a setup, right?
Persons walking, they're juggling with the coffee,
the textbook, all the clipboard,
and he says, on the elevator, he says,
could you just hold my cup while I write down your name
on my list of subjects in the experiment?
Okay, it's very innocent, right?
On the elevator, until you hold a cup of coffee,
which half the people get a hot cup,
half the people get a cold cup.
Then you read a description of a person,
it's just a paragraph, and you have to rate
whether you find the person described as warm or cold.
And if you had the warm cup of coffee,
you're more likely to describe that person
as a warm kind of a person, okay?
Now, these subjects have no idea,
they held a cup of coffee,
they probably didn't even think
whether it was warm or cold.
But something in their body that got warmed up
to the least degree possible, right?
That thought is still in their head.
So when they read a description,
somebody goes, oh, this seems like a warm person.
Or if it was a cold cup of coffee,
they say, oh, this seems like a cold, aloof kind of person
as far as I can tell, all right?
That little bit of difference.
So here's the lesson just so you got it.
If you want to take somebody
because you have a possible friendship
or romantic interest in that person,
are you better off going out for a warm cup of coffee
or giving them a cold glass of beer?
But for that first impression,
scientific research shows it's something warm will work.
It's not that powerful,
you're not gonna be able to control the world, okay?
But what it says is when we're in ambiguous situations,
we first meet somebody, we don't really know them.
Little things can start us off on one path
or can start us off on another path.
Surprisingly little things.
Now, then they have to worry about a confound.
Can you imagine a confound here?
Think of the rats.
Who knows if the cup is cold or hot
besides the person holding it?
The examiner, right?
Okay, now maybe the examiner doesn't try to do this,
but maybe the examiner no matter what says,
over in the warm condition and I'm smiling
because this is gonna be nice,
I'm helping this person feel good.
And here's the aloof condition,
I'm giving it, and we're all gonna be miserable.
And the examiner knows it because they know
if they have a hot or cold cup of coffee.
So maybe the person's not vibing to the coffee,
they're vibing to the expression or feeling
or sentiment of the examiner, right?
Who understands what's going on?
So they do one more experiment where they give,
have you seen these hot and icy therapeutic packs
that you could make hot or cold?
Okay, now somebody else makes it hot or cold.
The experimenter has no idea whether it was hot or cold.
So it's what we call double blind.
The person doesn't know it's relevant, the experimenter.
They rate the pad and now, this moves it a little bit,
they either get, after this thing is over,
they're told it's a product evaluation of the pad,
but they either got a hot pad or a cold pad.
And they could either choose to one of two rewards,
a Snapple beverage or a dollar gift certificate,
whichever you like better.
Okay, you had two little things you could do.
But here's the big decision, do you get it for yourself
where we can send it for you to a friend?
We can send them the Snapple or the certificate.
If the people got a cold pad, 75% of the times they say,
please give it to me right now, I'll take it.
If they had a warm pad, 46% of the,
the majority of the time they actually send it
to their friend.
That pad difference moved quite substantially,
the likelihood that you take it for yourself
or you give it away, quite substantially.
If you're a charity trying to get people to donate
or you wanna get help from somebody,
a 75, 25% success rate is a lot worse
than a 54% right, it's a doubling,
a doubling of whether you keep it for yourself
or you're generous to your friend.
Just that cup of coffee, it's just that therapeutic pad.
I'm gonna do two more and then go to the video.
How about money?
When you think about money,
I don't mean traumatic things about money,
just a little bit about money.
How does it influence how you relate to other people?
Okay, here's the experiment.
The idea is that money on average,
when you just think a little bit about it
and I'll show you how ridiculously little
they think about it,
their hypothesis is that money makes you think
about self-reliance, you earn your money,
you have your bank account,
compared to situations where you're not thinking about money.
So here's what they did.
They had people come in in three conditions.
They either, and they had to unscramble sentences.
You have no idea what's going on, right?
You got a sentence like, cold at desk outside is,
which you would make into a good sentence,
or high as salary desk paying, okay?
So you just make those, you scramble those words around,
but the money condition has a word like salary in it.
Or you get the neutral sentences
that have no money reference,
and you see a monopoly money in the corner of the room.
Okay, so we're not talking like,
people just sent you your tuition bill, okay?
Or whatever, or you just found out that you're something
terrible happened financially, or you won the lottery.
It's monopoly money, okay?
It's just like the idea of money in them, all right?
Okay, and then they give you a task to do,
and the experimenter, as he or she leaves the room,
they say, it's a pretty hard task, you may want some help.
So just come and get me, I'm glad to help you, not a problem.
So what happens?
Here's a probability of getting help,
and it's incredibly more for the control groups
that did the sentences without money,
and way less, not only for the people who unscramble
the sentence with the word salary,
but also way less if they saw monopoly money in the corner.
The mere idea of money, not money given to you,
not financial trauma or financial gain,
the mere idea of money makes you less willing
to get up and get help.
So the positive, it makes you more self-reliant.
The negative is people were less willing
to help somebody.
Now the end, as the examiner comes in and says,
you know, I'm an undergraduate like you,
I've got huge pressure to get this paper in,
can you help me code, can you help me score up a few sheets?
Okay, people were twice as much willing to help
if they just did the neutral things,
than if they unscrambled the money sentences
or saw the monopoly money in the corner of the room.
Cause just that thought about money goes like,
man, okay, self-reliance, we're all in it for ourselves.
Okay, I've got my money, you've got your money.
You know, good luck, we're all, we're all, we're all out.
Okay, self-reliance can be a good thing,
but it doesn't necessarily go with helping people
very much also, yeah.
So there's no relationship to people though,
like, there's just monopoly money
and it's just suspicious that a lot of the money's
moving there, that's why you're not going to help.
It could, yeah, the monopoly money, I agree with you,
maybe that's why they also had the one
where you just get the scrambled sentences.
Okay, I agree with you, these are all,
you know, you could think, there's many, many ways
to think about this.
Okay, the last example that I just kind of want to show you
is dating behavior, all right.
And the way, again, an experiment can challenge
various ideas, so, and this is specifically
about dating between men and women.
The story, to the extent it's been studied,
would be a little bit different
if you're dating within a sex.
So, for dating between men and women,
who is more selective in their dating choices, do you think?
Who's more willing to date widely, or a lot?
Or less, you know, what's your thought
if you have to generalize about men and women
on average in your,
no, okay, thank you, all right.
Okay, so, an evolutionary psychologist,
and I love evolutionary psychology,
but it drives me crazy too, okay.
Evolutionary psychologists will go,
well, because, you know, by evolutionary theory,
men have to go and make as many offspring
as they can to keep their genes going,
women have to be more selective.
It takes nine months to bear a baby,
it takes nine seconds to do the male part, right?
Okay.
Estimated.
Okay, so, you know, so this might or might not be true.
It's kind of fun, we all laugh about it.
All of us find it kind of amusing
to sort of think about, you know, if we, so,
but how would we actually know
if this is vaguely true on average?
How would we actually know if men
for dating behavior are more,
how would we even, is that true,
is that a, you know, bad myth, the bad rap, or whatever, yeah.
Getting my sides?
Yeah, thank you very much.
So there's an entire research enterprise out there now
that uses online dating sites,
which, of course, it's only in the last 20 years
or something, you know, that they've existed, I think,
so it wasn't before.
And the other one that's been a treasure trove of data,
a speed dating environments, okay,
where you can observe things and measure things.
And those studies have shown, for example,
that online dating on average men are one and a half times
more likely to send email offerings, you know,
dates to a woman than the other way around,
compared to women.
And in speed dating, too,
men are more likely to indicate there
would be happy to date a person they met than women.
So there's objective evidence that this is true
on average in this society at this time.
And so everybody's, oh yeah,
this shows the evolutionary psychology.
Evolutionary psychology is crazy,
because on the one hand, it's certainly the case
that our minds and brains evolved through evolution, okay.
So there's something about the history we went through
as a species that matters for who we are now.
That's gotta be the case.
On the other hand, it was a different world
before internet dating and speed dating, right.
I mean, it's hard to know how those things line up exactly.
So here's the fun thing.
It turns out that on average in speed dating,
a typical speed dating event will have like four minutes,
right, so you typically have women sitting at desks,
is it, almost always they set it up that way.
And the men are sitting in chairs in front of the desk
and they meet and they talk for four minutes.
The bell rings, the men jump up
and they shift over one station, right.
And then what happens is,
for each time you meet a person,
you fill out a card that says yes or no,
I'd be willing to have a date with a person.
And if you have two yeses from the man and the woman,
the speed dating organizer exchanges the information
so they can make direct contact.
Is that for some, okay, all right.
And men make more yes responses
and it turns out, this doesn't have to be this way,
but almost, from my reading,
that almost every speed dating thing
has the men rotating around, okay.
And the women sitting there,
waiting for the men to rotate around.
So let's just ask this question.
What happens if the women rotate,
which almost never happens,
but they did this experimentally.
They said, for half of the speed dating sessions,
the men will be sitting at the table
and the women will stand up
and move a chair over every four minutes.
The bell rings, so the women are moving and rotating.
And here's the results.
Basically what's showing on the left
are when the men rotate, the standard condition,
the first one is romantic desire.
Men feel more romantic desire
on average for the partner they sit with.
They feel that more chemistry is happening
with the person they sit with.
And on the bottom left corner,
they also are more likely to give a yes response.
I would like a date with this person, okay.
But reverse the roles, have the women rotating
and look at these bars, there's no difference at all.
You completely wipe out the male-female difference
in self-reported romantic desire per person,
self-reported chemistry they think is happening,
and the yes-no responses that I would have at it.
You completely eliminate it
when the women are rotating, it's flat even.
So that's the result, what does it suggest?
What happened to the evolutionary psychology?
It disappeared just by having the women
rotate around their own.
It suggests, and we don't know this with certainty,
but there are people that are following this up
who are interested in this,
it suggests that there's something about
getting up and approaching that person,
your body going, here I come, okay.
I'm not sitting in my chair, hanging out,
it's like, here I come.
That makes a person energized, feel more romantic,
feel more chemistries happening,
and more likely to ask on a date.
And it doesn't matter whether you're a man or a woman at all.
It's the getting up and that physical approach,
just, you're more invested, you're more out there,
who knows what it is.
Completely eliminates what everybody had said
is an ancient, inevitable evolutionary difference
between men and women.
And this isn't to say there might not be
some of those streaks in us, who knows.
But speed dating is not showing that, okay.
All you gotta do is have the women rotate,
and you completely eliminate what's thought to be
some hardwired biological difference on this dimension.
Now, talking about that, when we do experiments like this
that look at sort of fun things like dating around a thing
or age difference between a five-year-old
and a 20-year-old or 20-year-old and an 80-year-old,
cultures, there's lots of experiments to compare,
say, Western cultures versus Eastern Asian cultures.
We'll talk about that later in the course
in terms of behaviors.
Genes, whether you have one gene or another.
All those things, are those independent variables?
No.
We can't assign you randomly to be a man or a woman,
younger or old, to come from the United States
or Japan or China, or to have this gene or that gene.
It's not that we couldn't do stuff,
you know, in some monstrous world,
but not ethically, and it's never gonna happen, right?
So, whenever you have science that talks about
differences between men and women, or young and old,
or cultures, or genes, it's not really
a completely independent manipulation.
We can't assign you randomly, and so it means
everything in the world about what it means to be
a man or a woman, a 20-year-old or an 80-year-old,
come from this continent or that continent,
have this gene or that gene.
Those are not things we can freely manipulate,
and you have to be extra cautious
in interpreting those kinds of studies,
because we can't randomly assign you to condition,
we just can't.
Okay, and I didn't talk about the fact that we,
up until this moment, we've made every conclusion
a complete generality about human nature,
and people are different,
one from the other individual differences,
we'll talk about that later in the course too.
So, for the last couple of minutes,
I wanna talk about this.
Folk psychology, you know,
everybody has ideas about psychology,
so if you have this piece of paper,
if you would zoom through it,
ideas about people in psychology,
and just where there is some scientific evidence,
if you just zoom down on Mark, yes or no,
on average, do offices attract?
On average, is familiarity, breed contempt?
On average, more people present in an emergency,
are you more likely to get some help?
On average, are there such things as visual learners
and verbal learners, and if they got
the right kind of instruction,
that would help them in school?
Is hypnosis baloney?
Dissubliminal advertising work,
you know, when things are presented,
so you don't see them below consciousness,
does it help you buy something?
Just playing Mozart to an infant boost
their intelligence, Mozart effect?
Is old age on average associated with dissatisfaction?
If you're unsure of your answer when taking a test,
I'm gonna tell you the science about this,
it's best to stick with your first hunch.
Practically every website tells you that,
have you heard that many times?
Okay, I'm gonna tell you what the actual evidence
is about that and how they get that in a moment.
Ulcers are caused primarily by stress,
a positive attitude can stave off cancer.
Raising children similarly leads to similarities
in their adult personalities, you know.
Low self-esteem is the major cause
of psychological problems.
People's responses and the ink block tests
tell us a lot about their personalities.
Interviews help identify those most likely
to succeed in medical school.
Okay.
I'll give you a minute.
Okay, a bunch of these we'll come back to in the course.
The answer for all these is this
and there's evidence to it all.
So I'm gonna tell you about four of them for 10 minutes, okay?
One of the ones you might wanna know most about
is the changing your initial hunch answer.
Okay, how do you know that?
So that people have gone back over test scores
and look where people crossed out an answer
or erased an answer,
that's the best source of evidence they have
in large samples
and people are twice as likely to give a better,
the correct answer than to move to a wrong answer.
That's the empirical evidence, okay?
So it's a fantastically interesting disconnect
that you see so many places and teachers advise you
go with your first hunch when you're unsure.
The empirical evidence is you're much more likely
to be correct when you go with your best final answer, okay?
All right, I mean, of course, you're not sure
so you're gonna miss a fair bit
but you're twice as likely to come out
with the correct answer
when you go with your best possible answer
so that people who crossed out their answers
or erased their answers,
they were twice as likely to move to a good answer
than leave behind a good answer, yeah.
You know that maybe it's not like they pick an answer
and then just switch their answer
and then taking the advice and going back to thinking
about why they didn't.
Yeah, that's an excellent question.
We don't know, they've kind of gone like five times
back and forth.
The assumption has been on average
that people will go once back and forth
but you're right but ask yourself the other question too.
What's the evidence ever that going with your hunches
and nobody's been able to show that, okay?
So where there's evidence is all in favor of best answer
and nobody's shown evidence
that hunch is the best way to go empirically.
That doesn't mean that sometimes it doesn't happen
but on average that's the way that ends.
But your question, your point's excellent.
Okay, so how about Rorschach test?
Every psychology program, clinical psychologists
in the country is required to learn
how to administer and evaluate a Rorschach.
You know this?
So this obviously shows, obviously it shows
some sort of horrible sex act between animals and, no.
No, it's a, yeah, you know all these kinds of tests
you're supposed to read it and then the examiner listens
to you and they figure out something, right?
Okay, there's been about 10,000 publications about this.
There's no evidence that there's anything predictive
or correct about this test, none, zero, none, okay?
People argue it, people give it, you know?
People have to learn how to give this test.
So this is a disconnect that happens a lot
between clinical stuff and experimental work.
I mean those, you know, researchers can't grasp
why people still give this.
Medical school interviews, those of you
who will apply to medical school will get interviews,
who get interviews for jobs,
who get interviews for all kinds of things in your life.
What's the evidence that interviews
are any good for anything?
How could you know whether interviews are good for anything?
A company interviews you, a university interviews you.
How would you even decide whether,
so I can tell you that socialist psychologists
have shown repeatedly that interviews
are cesspools for discrimination
because people tend to like people who are like them, okay?
You know, oh, you went to MIT, you know, yeah,
course nine, you know, then you go,
oh man, this is gonna be good, right?
Or I went to Caltech, we didn't like MIT people,
we thought they were a little bit snobby or something,
and I go, oh, that's not gonna be so good, right?
Okay, so, you know, socialist psychologists have shown
that if you just vary information in practice interviews,
people tend to like people who are like them
by background, by appearance, and so on.
On average, they try not to, they try to be fair, but,
okay, so we know that.
But how about me, okay, so here's what Yale,
here's what they did.
Yale compared students who were accepted
or rejected on the basis of an interview,
so they all had scores that got them to the interview.
And then they looked at them where they went in pairs
or larger than pairs to other medical schools.
So let's say you got accepted by Yale,
and you were accepted or rejected on the interview,
but you ended up as two students at Penn,
or two students at Michigan, okay?
You're sitting next to each other, I'll just, right?
One of you was accepted by interview at Yale,
one of you was not.
Who does better at that other place?
They're dead even.
The interview added nothing for predicting grade point average
or completion of medical school.
Here's one more example.
The University of Texas enlarged in the midst of their,
Houston, in the midst of their interviews,
it enlarged from 150 to 200 students.
They had interviewed 800, 150 who came
were among their top ones.
They interviewed them, they liked them, they came.
And then they had, and all of a sudden,
because the state legislature said,
we're by law, man, they need to take 50 more.
They took 50 more who didn't do so well in the interview,
okay?
Those 50 more performed identically
to the ones who got in with a successful interview.
They couldn't find a difference between them.
Now, there's at least one thing you might think
the interview might have done, but we don't know,
but people, what do you think it might have done?
So the outcome was your grades in medical school
and your likelihood of completing medical school.
What else could an interview have been relevant for?
Maybe, maybe, maybe.
Something about bedside manner or how you relate to people.
Maybe, maybe, maybe, but there's no evidence
that's true, okay?
Now you're starting to grasp at straws.
So there's no evidence that interview processes
make any difference anywhere,
but everybody does interviews all the ways
because we always think we're kind of good judges
of human nature or something, okay?
So interviews, it's very hard to tell
that they ever do anything.
So here's my last thing, self-esteem.
You cannot watch Oprah or Dr. Phil
without some discussion of self-esteem at some moment.
And it sounds good to everybody.
I mean, nobody would wish for you as a parent or friend
for you to have low self-esteem.
And in fact, higher self-esteem is correlated
with higher initiative and persistence,
happiness and emotional resilience,
and also, unfortunately,
with people who are narcissistic and bullies, okay?
I mean, I mean, and how they measure it,
just so you know, because this is a problem too,
like how do you measure it?
You have, there's several scales,
but the most widely used scale is this Rosenberg scale.
So you have that too if you wanna try it out on yourself, okay?
Okay, self-report.
And when they reviewed 15,000 studies some years ago,
they could find no evidence
that higher self-esteem leads to better things.
It all seemed the other way around.
That like doing better at things led to higher self-esteem,
okay?
They could never find that pushing your self-esteem up
doesn't.
Having said that, I can tell you as a parent
of two young kids or if you have friends
and you care about them and you know this,
we like to praise people to build up their self-esteem,
right?
We tell them, you're awesome.
Someday you'll go to MIT and I know you will, okay?
You're a wonderful person and you're smart
and you're beautiful and, you know,
parents want their children and teachers too
to grow up and thrive and build up that self-esteem.
So how can, and the easiest way to do that is praise, right?
Just telling your kid how awesome he or she is
or your younger sibling how awesome he or she is.
Get their self-esteem up.
So the last thing I'm gonna tell you
and then we'll be done in about three minutes is
work from Carol Dweck that shows you how danger it is
to encounter productive it is to have
praise where you don't think through its relation
to people and in one sentence we'll talk about
are you gonna succeed in life by your effort
or by your talent?
What's a bigger question than that?
Wherever you get to in your life,
it's gonna be based on your effort or your talent or both.
I'll just have a sentence about that now.
So here's the experiment she did with fifth graders.
She had them perform a pretty hard task
and afterwards, randomly, they were either praised
for their intelligence.
So a person said to them, you, fifth grader,
you are so smart, I can't believe how great you did
on that fifth grader, okay?
Or they were praised for their hard work.
This shows a lot of hard work, okay?
Different kid and some kids got no praise at all.
In this experiment, okay?
Now, then they get a task that's even a little bit harder.
How does the different kind of praise influence things?
And here was the finding.
If you were praised for your intelligence,
you did worse on the second test.
If you were praised for your hard work, you did better.
If nobody said anything, your performance didn't change.
And the idea is this, you understand?
Praise for your intelligence, you did worse on a hard task.
Praise for your effort, you did better.
And here's the idea that if we praise people
for their intelligence to build up their self-esteem,
they start to care more about how their performance
reflects on them than the performance itself.
Because if I, you're trying to prove
that you're an intelligent person.
You care less, the students who get that kind of praise
for their intelligence, they persist less
in a difficult task, they say they don't enjoy challenges.
Why?
They just wanna ace everything to keep proving they're smart.
Okay?
The kids who get praised for effort,
they're kinda like, okay, I'm gonna make some mistakes,
but I'm just gonna keep going,
because with effort I can do things sometimes.
And it turns out that it makes a remarkable thing.
And so Dweck, we'll come back to this,
talks about, you can imbue your intelligence as a trait.
I have only so much.
Or as a growth, the harder I work, the smarter I get,
but I have to do the hard work to get there, okay?
And we live in a society that often goes by
fixed traits, American Idol, the harder to work,
the better you sing, or who has the talent is discovered.
Who has the talent is discovered, right?
Okay, right?
Because the idea is, you have a certain amount
of musical talent, and now the judges show
and you break into the world and you're a famous singer,
right?
So ask yourself this, when you are good at what you do,
is it because something in your genes
or an environment made you good at,
or is it because you try really hard?
So Malcolm Gladwell has this statement
that's floating around, gets a lot of attention,
that anybody can become great at anything
if they work on it for 10,000 hours.
So how much of your success in the past,
currently in the future, is gonna be based on your effort,
and how much is it gonna be based on your talents,
and how would we know that?
And we're a very talent-oriented society,
and it seems like the more we encourage effort,
maybe the more people might flourish.
So we talked about how psychology and science,
experiments, brief history of psychology experimentation,
some issues in experimentation,
and then some psychological topics,
and some practical information
for being generous and kind and winning friends rapidly.
Okay, thanks very much.